Nicole: So, what do you do
if your system gets infected?
The first step in incident response
if you are concerned that a device or
system may be infected is containment.
It’s important to disconnect from the
internet and the network you’re on as this
will prevent any more data being sent to
a malware server or will stop it spreading
to other computers on your network.
Stay offline as much as possible unless
needing to download any legitimate
tools to help get rid of the malware.
Disconnect after the download
is complete and stay offline
until the malware is removed.
Opening a system in safe mode or
safe boot allows only the minimum
software and programs to load.
Logging in to accounts should be
avoided whilst removing malware so
as not to expose passwords through
copy and paste function or by 'show
password' because 'key logger' malware
is a common component of malware.
Also avoid sharing any personal details or
information whilst a device is infected.
Check activity monitors for malicious
applications especially if a suspicious
update or application has been installed.
Run a malware scanner.
These can remove most standard infections
however if your antivirus software hasn't
already picked this up you should try
another scanner which may be able to
detect more existing and emerging malware
such as a heuristic antimalware solution.
Verify the browser homepage this will
involve connecting to the internet and
clear the cache, this is the temporary
storage location where data is saved.
If malware removal is unsuccessful,
it may be that the operating system
may need to be reinstalled along with
applications and programs from scratch.
If everything is backed up it shouldn't
be a problem but contacting the system
suppliers help desk may be necessary.
This process is exactly the same for large
companies and organisations but is usually
handled by tools that do these steps
or a dedicated incident response team.